A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, World Affairs, Series Q FA326
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Institute of Pacific Relations
  - Institute of Pacific Relations - American Institute of Pacific Relations
    Requests for aid granted by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Rockefeller Foundation to finance meetings. John D. Rockefeller 3rd elected member of American Council of Institute but declined membership. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $155,000 between 1925 and 1935. Activities of Institute. Attacks on Institute. Comments by Arthur W. Packard. Interest of Rockefellers in work of Institute. Comments by Yorke Allen. Investigation for communist infiltration. Loss of tax exemption. Move to Vancouver, British Columbia. Correspondents include Raymond B. Fosdick, Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, E. C. Carter, Gerard Swope, Yorke Allen.
    213
    - March 1925-December 1936 (Box 9, Folder 62)
    - January 1937-November 1948 (Box 9, Folder 63)
    - December 1948-March 1950 (Box 9, Folder 64)
    - April 1950-March 1951 (Box 9, Folder 65)
    - April 1951-October 1951 (Box 9, Folder 66)
    - November 1951-December 1960 (Box 9, Folder 67)
  - Institute of Pacific Relations - American Institute of Pacific Relations - Pledges; 1928, 1931, 1933, 1928-1933 (Box 10, Folder 68)
    Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Institute of Pacific Relations - American Institute of Pacific Relations - East and West Association, 1941-1949 (Box 10, Folder 69)
    Pearl S. Buck supports society which will duplicate Institute of Pacific Relations (IPR) work. Asks Rockefellers for aid, declined.
  - Institute of Pacific Relations - American Institute of Pacific Relations - Laurance S. Rockefeller Contributions, 1938-1953 (Box 10, Folder 70)
    Since 1941, annual contributions of $25.00 till 1949.
  - Institute of Pacific Relations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd attended conference in Kyoto in 1929. Relations with American Council of Institute. Work of the Institute for the government. Confidential 1942 report from China. Other reports on conditions in the Far East. Appeals for aid. Institute's defense against subversive charges. John D. Rockefeller 3rd very inactive after 1950 although he remained a member. Council dissolved in December 1961. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, F. V. Field, E. C. Carter, Arthur W. Packard.
    - January 1938-August 1944 (Box 10, Folder 71)
    - January 1945-March 1950 (Box 10, Folder 72)
    - August 1950-October 1952 (Box 10, Folder 73)
    - November 1952-June 1953 (Box 10, Folder 74)
    - December 1953-December 1961 (Box 10, Folder 75)
  - Institute of Pacific Relations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - Contributions, 1933-1949 (Box 11, Folder 76)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd's annual support for Institute: $100-$500. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Arthur W. Packard, Frederick V. Field.
  - Institute of Pacific Relations - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - Contributions - Gift, December 23, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 77)
    800 shares of Socony Vacuum Oil Company stock.
  - Institute of Pacific Relations - A. Kohlberg, November 1944-August 1949 (Box 11, Folder 78)
    Controversy between Kohlberg and directors of Institute. Kohlberg claimed staff was communistic. File contains a variety of his charges against Institute. Denials by Institute but no real analysis of situation. All material sent to Rockefeller office but not commented on. Correspondents include Alfred Kohlberg, Arthur W. Packard.
  - Institute of Pacific Relations - A. Kohlberg, September 1949-November 1949 (Box 11, Folder 79)
  - Institute of Pacific Relations - Institute of Ethnic Affairs, Inc., 1935-June 1946 (Box 11, Folder 80)
    Research agency for better relations between races. Nelson A. Rockefeller's interest in the Spanish-speaking people in the United States division. Federal funds. Forming of Community Service Clubs, Inc. in 1946. One contribution; later appeals declined. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard, Jane Pijoan, John Collier.
    213.2
  - Institute of Pacific Relations - Institute of Ethnic Affairs, Inc., July 1946-May 1950 (Box 11, Folder 81)
  - Institute of Pacific Relations - Institute of Ethnic Affairs, Inc. - Contributions, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 82)
    Nelson A. Rockefeller gift $1,000. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller.
- National Defense
  - National Defense, 1940-1942 (Box 12, Folder 83)
    Nelson A. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. urge overall master plan for preparing nation for war. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. writes to New York "Times" urging plan in 1940. Request for gifts to defense projects, information on obtaining defense contracts, invitations to patriotic rallies and meetings. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, David Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    173
  - National Defense, 1940-1942 (Box 12, Folder 0083A)
  - National Defense - War Organizations - War Chests, 1918 (Box 12, Folder 84)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. works to have united appeal for work of Young Mens Christian Association (YMCA), Knights of Columbus and Jewish Welfare and others with soldiers. Raymond B. Fosdick points out duplication in relief agencies at end of war. Correspondents include John R. Mott, George Vincent, Raymond B. Fosdick, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - National Defense - Army and Navy War Activities
    Requests for gifts to various endeavors: Coast Guard Academy chapel, Protestant committee for Army chaplains, Naval Reserve committees. Some granted, some declined--all small. Civil defense. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    - March 1941-December 1948 (Box 12, Folder 85)
    - February 1949-1951 (Box 12, Folder 86)
    - February 1949-1951 (Box 12, Folder 0086A)
    - June 1952-July 1961 (Box 12, Folder 87)
    - June 1952-July 1961 (Box 12, Folder 0087A)
  - National Defense - Army and Navy War Activities - American Women's Voluntary Services, Inc., 1941-1954 (Box 12, Folder 88)
    Abby Aldrich Rockefeller contribution. Later requests declined.
  - National Defense - Army and Navy War Activities - Army Relief Society - Governor's Island, 1920-1941 (Box 12, Folder 89)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $200 annually for recreational activities on the island, 1920-1931. Abby Aldrich Rockefeller made several small contributions in 1940's. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard.
  - National Defense - Army and Navy War Activities - Army and Navy Legion of Valor, 1944-1950 (Box 12, Folder 90)
    Appeals for aid declined. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard.
  - National Defense - Universal Military Training League, 1916-1923 (Box 12, Folder 91)
    League in 1916 endorses Universal Military Training for six months for all 19 year olds. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. favors idea, contributes $5,000. No action after 1918. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Raymond B. Fosdick.
  - National Defense - War Activities, 1917-1928 (Box 13, Folder 92)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s concern over health conditions in camps. Donation of $250 toward social work among soldiers and sailors at Mt. Desert. Contribution of $1,000 toward music in service camps. Other small contributions. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller, Sr.
  - National Defense - War Activities - Canadian Club, 1918-1919 (Box 13, Folder 93)
    Relief for dependents of Canadian and American soldiers serving in Canadian armed forces. Dependents were located primarily in New York City. $2,000 gift in 1918.
  - National Defense - War Activities - Col. W. Hayward, 15th Regiment, New York, 1917-1919 (Box 13, Folder 94)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s gift of $1,000 to Negro infantry regiment.
  - National Defense - War Activities - Contributions for Home Defense and Patriotic Contributions - Lists, 1916-1919 (Box 13, Folder 95)
  - National Defense - War Activities - Home Defense League of Tarrytown, 1917-1918 (Box 13, Folder 96)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s gift of $200.
  - National Defense - War Activities - Lakewood Home Guards, 1917 (Box 13, Folder 97)
    $100.
  - National Defense - War Activities - Library War Fund, 1917 (Box 13, Folder 98)
    $2,500.
  - National Defense - War Activities - Knights of Columbus, 1917-1918 (Box 13, Folder 99)
    $6,000.
  - National Defense - War Activities - Mayor's Committee on National Defense, 1917-1918 (Box 13, Folder 100)
    New York City. Gifts of $1,000 and $2,500.
  - National Defense - War Activities - Westchester County Committee on Safety, 1917-1918 (Box 13, Folder 101)
    $9,000 from John D. Rockefeller, Sr. and John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - National Defense - Navy League of United States, 1909-1960 (Box 13, Folder 102)
    Requests that John D. Rockefeller, Jr. join League, make contributions, declined. Laurance S. Rockefeller declined joining League in 1947. $1,000 contribution in 1952 by Laurance S. Rockefeller. Laurance S. Rockefeller on "benefit committee for showing of John Paul Jones." Continue to decline joining League. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, Arthur W. Packard, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    173.1
  - National Defense - Navy League of United States, 1909-1960 (Box 13, Folder 0102A)
  - National Defense - National Marine League of United States, 1915-1923 (Box 13, Folder 103)
    League to foster an American Merchant Marine. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. paid $100, became life member; loaned $2,000 toward magazine support; loan not repaid. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Buchanan Houston, Willard S. Richardson, August Belmont.
    173.2
  - National Defense - Soldiers' Sailors' and Airmen's Club, Inc., 1926-1960 (Box 13, Folder 104)
    Service men's club which continued in operation after World War I. Investigations of club by Rockefeller office. Contributions by John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, David Rockefeller. Correspondents include Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur W. Packard, David Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller.
  - National Defense - Soldiers' Sailors' and Airmen's Club, Inc., 1926-1960 (Box 13, Folder 0104A)
  - National Defense - Soldiers' Sailors' and Airmen's Club, Inc. - Contributions, 1917-1946 (Box 13, Folder 105)
  - National Defense - Soldiers' Sailors' and Airmen's Club, Inc. - Contributions, 1946 (Box 13, Folder 0105A)
  - National Defense - Navy Club, 1919-1934 (Box 13, Folder 106)
    Appeals for aid to recreation club for sailors in Manhattan, declined. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    173.21
  - National Defense - Aviation, 1916-1935 (Box 14, Folder 107)
    Requests for aid in flights across Atlantic, declined. Descriptions of air routes of the future. Offers of investment possibilities, declined. Laurance S. Rockefeller contributes to Air Force Association. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    173.3
  - National Defense - Aviation, 1938-1961 (Box 14, Folder 108)
  - National Defense - Aviation, 1938-1961 (Box 14, Folder 0108A)
  - National Defense - National Security League, 1917-1942 (Box 14, Folder 109)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed $45,000 to League during war. League changed to better schools, anti-communist campaign after war, promoted military training, economic preparedness. But no further contributions were made. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Raymond B. Fosdick, Thomas M. Debevoise, Willard S. Richardson, Starr J. Murphy.
    173.4
  - National Defense - National Security League - Contribution - April 2, 1917; Military Training Bill, 1915-1917 (Box 14, Folder 110)
  - National Defense - National Security League - Contribution - Committee on Patriotism Through Education, 1917-1918 (Box 14, Folder 111)
  - National Defense - American Defense Society, 1916-1939 (Box 14, Folder 112)
    Encouraged military training, handling of arms, citizen soldiery. Issued propaganda against Germany during the war. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed $100 in 1920 toward education campaign in American business sponsored by League. This was the only Rockefeller contribution. Correspondents included John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Starr J. Murphy, Willard S. Richardson, Arthur W. Packard.
    173.5
  - National Defense - Playground and Recreation Association - War Camp Community Service, 1917-1919 (Box 14, Folder 113)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contribution to Service. Providing recreation for off-duty soldiers. Concern with morality. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Raymond F. Fosdick.
    173.51
  - National Defense - Playground and Recreation Association - War Camp Community Service - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Pledge, 1917-1919 (Box 14, Folder 114)
  - National Defense - Playground and Recreation Association - War Camp Community Service - Bureau of Social Hygiene Pledge, 1917-1918 (Box 14, Folder 115)
    $25,000 to support police work around army camps to prevent young girls from flinging themselves at soldiers.
  - National Defense - Commission on Training Camp Activities, 1917-1919 (Box 14, Folder 116)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributes small amounts to camp work, supervised by Rockefeller Brothers Fund. K.B. Davis lent by Bureau of Social Hygiene to study vice conditions in vicinity of camps. Correspondents include Raymond F. Fosdick, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., K. B. Davis.
  - National Defense - Council on National Defense - Committee on Labor, 1917-1930 (Box 15, Folder 117)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. a member of Committee on Labor, National Council of Defense. S. Gompers, Chairman of Committee. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s rough notes on meting held May 15, 1917. Jr. accepted membership as means of furthering his ideals on relations of labor and management. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed $1,000 to work of Committee. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Same Gompers, V. E. Macy.
    173.52
  - National Defense - Commander Byrd Expeditions, 1925-1929 (Box 15, Folder 118)
    E. Ford and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. united to provide funds for Byrd's first Arctic expedition but change in Byrd's plans voids promise for 1925. Pledge renewed in 1926, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $20,000. Byrd sent John D. Rockefeller, Jr. eiderdown coat, flag. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. increased gift to $30,000. Wires from Byrd while on expedition of 1926, newspaper accounts. Byrd's desire to "play the game as it should be played." Byrd describes his 1927 transatlantic attempt as a move to improve "international friendship." Wires from 1929 Antarctic expedition which John D. Rockefeller, Jr. also helped finance. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contributions on a personal basis. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. refused to finance 1933-1934 expedition. Dinners in tribute to Byrd. Correspondents include Edsel Ford, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Raymond B. Fosdick, R. E. Byrd.
    173.6
  - National Defense - Commander Byrd Expeditions, 1930-1940 (Box 15, Folder 119)
  - National Defense - Commander Byrd Expeditions - Floyd Bennett, 1928-1930 (Box 15, Folder 120)
    Lindbergh's serum delivery.
  - National Defense - Commander Byrd - Antarctic Expedition, 1927-1929 (Box 15, Folder 121)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. again joins Edsel Ford and others in financing Byrd expedition. John D. Rockefeller, Sr.'s contribution to Antarctic expedition exceeded $150,000. Friendly family messages here. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, R. E. Byrd, Raymond B. Fosdick.
  - National Defense - Military Training Camps Association, 1916-1927, 1940-1951 (Box 15, Folder 122)
    Plattsburg idea--summer training for civilians under officers of U. S. Army. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. supports idea, primarily because it brings together men of different social standing on a basis of equality. Association urged universal military training. No Rockefeller interest after 1918. Appeals continued through 1940, when John D. Rockefeller, Jr. made $2,000 contribution. Winthrop Rockefeller attends 1940 Plattsburg camp. No later interest. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John Platt.
    173.7
  - National Defense - Compulsory Military Training Law, 1940-1941 (Box 15, Folder 123)
    Newspaper clippings on John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s sons registering for the draft.
    173.8
  - National Defense - National War Services Act, 1943-1944 (Box 15, Folder 124)
    Citizens' committee urging passage of National Service Law to aid war effort. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributes $1,000, offers to underwrite second $1,000. Contributes second $1,000 in 1943; $2,000 in 1944. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Thomas M. Debevoise.
    173.81
  - National Defense - Universal Military Training, 1945-1955 (Box 15, Folder 125)
    Pros and cons of Universal Military Training. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    173.82
  - National Defense - Universal Military Training - Citizens' Committee for Military Training of Young Men, Inc., 1945-1947 (Box 15, Folder 126)
    Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard.
    173.821
    DR material removed to Folder 126A.
  - National Defense - Universal Military Training - Citizens' Committee for Military Training of Young Men, Inc., 1945-1947 (Box 15, Folder 0126A)
    David Rockefeller contribution.
  - National Defense - Universal Military Training - Citizens' Committee for the Universal Military Training of Young Men, 1944-1945 (Box 15, Folder 127)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution.
  - National Defense - National Economy League, 1932 (Box 16, Folder 128)
    Organization fighting to have costs of Veterans' benefit programs reduced. Nelson A. Rockefeller and Thomas M. Debevoise opposed to paying veterans' bonuses. Discuss with E. M. Hopkins, a bloc of college voters. R. E. Byrd very active in League. John D. Rockefeller, Sr. supported him in personal letters. League pressures Roosevelt and Congress; March 1933 wins its objectives. Byrd resigned in May 1933. Objective after 1934: balance budget. Contributions discontinued in 1935 because League was too political. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, Thomas M. Debevoise, E. M. Hopkins, R. E. Byrd, Arthur W. Packard.
    173.9
  - National Defense - National Economy League, 1933-1942 (Box 16, Folder 129)
  - National Defense - National Economy League - Contributions, 1933-1935 (Box 16, Folder 130)
  - National Defense - Soldiers - Vocational Training, Employment, etc., 1919-1932 (Box 16, Folder 131)
    Reemployment Bureau in New York City. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributes $5,000. Appeals for aid for individuals, declined. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur Woods.
    173.10
  - National Defense - Soldiers - Service Men, March 1921-July 1946 (Box 16, Folder 132)
    Proposed memorial to 27th Division; gifts for service men. Requests that John D. Rockefeller, Jr. act as sponsor for various activities, usually declined. Letters from soldiers and their families. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
  - National Defense - Soldiers - Service Men, October 1946-October 1952 (Box 16, Folder 133)
  - National Defense - Soldiers - Service Men, October 1946-October 1952 (Box 16, Folder 0133A)
  - National Defense - Soldiers - Pocantico Hills, 1941-1951 (Box 16, Folder 134)
    Pocantico Hills community gives watches to boys in service. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributes. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. sends boys from Pocantico a copy of a sermon by H. E. Fosdick, and a pamphlet by E. Rickenbacher. Personal letters of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to soldiers who thanked him. Summary of family relations with local veterans organizations 1921-1946 made in December 1946. Pocantico Hills held home-coming celebration. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. spoke and welcomed them home. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Sowden.
  - National Defense - Soldiers - Pocantico Hills - Distribution of Rickenbacker Article, 1944 (Box 16, Folder 135)
  - National Defense - Soldiers - Service Men - Veterans, December 1937-March 1955 (Box 17, Folder 136)
    Request for aid, routine, declined. Offer John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Americanism award 1953 by Grand Street Boy's Post, declined. Mary French Rockefeller and Nelson A. Rockefeller contributions. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Dana S. Creel, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
  - National Defense - Soldiers - Service Men - Veterans, December 1937-March 1955 (Box 17, Folder 0136A)
  - National Defense - Soldiers - Service Men - Veterans, May 1955-July 1961 (Box 17, Folder 137)
  - National Defense - Soldiers - Service Men - Veterans, May 1955-July 1961 (Box 17, Folder 0137A)
  - National Defense - War Manpower Conservation Committee, 1943-1944 (Box 17, Folder 138)
    Anna Rosenberg's Committee to conserve manpower refused by draft or discharged from service. Nelson A. Rockefeller made $5,000 contribution. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Nelson A. Rockefeller.
    173.101
  - National Defense - Veterans of Foreign Wars, 1926-1961 (Box 17, Folder 139)
    Appeals for contributions declined except for a few small donations to Tarrytown post. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Willard S. Richardson, Dana S. Creel, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    173.102
    DR material removed to Folder 139A.
  - National Defense - Veterans of Foreign Wars, 1926-1961 (Box 17, Folder 0139A)
    David Rockefeller contribution to Loyalty Parade Fund.
  - National Defense - Disabled American Veterans of World War I and World War II, 1926-1961 (Box 17, Folder 140)
    Appeals declined. Mary French Rockefeller small contributions. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur W. Packard, Mary French Rockefeller.
    173.103
  - National Defense - Disabled American Veterans of World War I and World War II, 1926-1961 (Box 17, Folder 0140A)
  - National Defense - American Veterans Committee, 1945-1957 (Box 17, Folder 141)
    Nelson A. Rockefeller contributed $5,000 in 1941; Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Winthrop Rockefeller, David Rockefeller contributions in 1947. Boys' total, 1945-1948, $21,000. Additional gifts in 1948 and 1949 by the boys. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, David Rockefeller.
    173.104
  - National Defense - American Veterans Committee, 1945-1957 (Box 17, Folder 0141A)
  - National Defense - American Veterans of World War II (AMVETS), 1949-1960 (Box 17, Folder 142)
    Requests for aid, declined. Office objects to method of solicitation. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, Anice Berthier.
    173.105
  - National Defense - American Legion, 1919-1945 (Box 18, Folder 143)
    Appeals for aid to local posts declined. $100 contributions to New York County Victory Ball. 1922-1926, several small contributions to New York posts.
    173.11
  - National Defense - American Legion, 1946-1960 (Box 18, Folder 144)
  - National Defense - American Legion - Contributions, 1920-1921 (Box 18, Folder 145)
  - National Defense - American Legion - Spencer-Kelly Post, Tarrytown, 1920-1946 (Box 18, Folder 146)
    Small contributions by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and John D. Rockefeller, Sr., purchase of tickets, etc. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, Robert W. Gumbel.
  - National Defense - Air Youth of America, 1941-1948 (Box 18, Folder 147)